Sarah Gertrude Knott papers
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 2: National Folk Festival Association business
  - National Folk Festival Association business (2/2), 1976 (Box-folder 4/2)
    Copies of a National Folk Festival Association news release, and copies of a photocopied National Folk Festival Association mailing to "member." One copy of the news release has a brief, handwritten notation by Knott. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: N.B. Joe [nota bene Joe?]. This folder is in the current folder.
  - NCTA business (folder 1/2), 1976-1978 (Box-folder 4/3)
    Correspondence with Knott, meeting minutes, and a memo and ballot regarding the NCTA board of directors. The correspondence includes information about the change in the organization's name, and the reasons behind it. A photocopy of Tradition (Winter 1977) has been moved to box-folder 12/16. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: NCTA letters and news.
  - NCTA business (folder 2/2), 1976-1978 (Box-folder 12/16)
    Photocopy of Tradition (Winter 1977), an NCTA publication/newsletter. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: NCTA letters and news. Relocated from box-folder 4/3.
  - First National Folk Festival held at Wolf Trap, 1978 (Box-folder 4/4)
    Photocopies of a typed page with handwritten notes (as part of the photocopy). Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Preparations for 1st Wolf Trap Farm Festival - work book. This folder is in the current folder.
  - National Folk Festival Association business and publicity, 1963-1978, undated (Box-folder 4/5)
    Typed correspondence (some with handwritten notations), newspaper clippings (photocopies and originals), promotional materials for folk events, and other materials. The folder includes a letter from Knott to Pauline Berkey (May 9, 1978) in which Knott says she is packing her papers to Western Kentucky University and the Library of Congress, and another letter to Vyts Beliajus (with the same date), with effectively the same information. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: 3 Book.
  - May Gadd interview transcript, and various National Folk Festival Association materials, 1960s-1970s (Box-folder 4/6)
    Original program for the concert "Folk Songs and Ballads of Abe Lincoln and the Civil War," presented by the Folklore Society of Greater Washington; a three-page letter to "Friends" from Knott, with opinions and reflections requested by Leonard Roberts, following the 33rd National Folk Festival (with criticism of Knott on page 2); a photocopy of Joe Hickerson's interview with May Gadd; a stapled photocopy of blank 1939 National Folk Festival letterhead, along with administrative information about the National Folk Festival; a photocopy of "Smithsonian Folklife Festival - National Folk Festival Association Plans," by Knott (1969), an original program for the 32nd National Folk Festival (1969), two copies of the final program for "Folklore and the Public Sector" (a meeting sponsored by three groups), and a photocopy of a newspaper article (1978). Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: An interview with May Gadd. This folder is in the current folder.
  - National Folk Festival Association publications, 1967-1977, undated (Box-folder 4/7)
    Includes publications from various years (some multiple copies), including NCTA's published calendar of festivals (1977). An original copy of the calendar of festivals (1978) has been relocated to box-folder 12/19. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: National Folk Festival Association: calendar of folk festivals (1/2).
  - Calendar of festivals, April-December 1978, April-Dec. 1978 (Box-folder 12/19)
    An original copy of NCTA's published calendar of festivals. Relocated from box-folder 4/7.
  - Questionnaire for folk-related organizations, 1979 (Box-folder 4/8)
    A questionnaire about how organizations serve their respective constituencies. Received in two separate, original folders: one undated, the other dated 1979. Previous folder headings: 1) Questionaires [sic] National Folk Fes. [Festival] and 2) Questionaire [sic] - SGK 1979; the first of these folders is in the current folder.
  - Letter from Bill Kornrich to Sarah Gertrude Knott, November 7, 1979 (Box-folder 4/9)
    Two copies of a letter (on National Folk Festival Association letterhead; one original and one photocopy). Topics include a reference to Joe Wilson having early National Folk Festival recordings "redone" (presumably copied) at the Library of Congress; also, a brief handwritten notation on the photocopy.
  - Address and welcome to the 41st National Folk Festival, circa 1979 (Box-folder 4/10)
    Photocopy of a typed document (probably written by Knott), with handwritten notes by Knott.
  - Original chart of embassy responses, undated (Box-folder 4/11)
    A chart with a compilation of responses to a questionnaire sent to embassies in Washington, The chart has been relocated to box-folder 12/25. D.C. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Embassy charts/Washington, D.C./National Folk Festival Association. This folder is in the current folder.
  - Handwritten chart, undated (Box-folder 12/25)
    Possibly a compilation of responses to a questionnaire sent to from embassies in Washington, D.C. Relocated from box-folder 4/11.
  - National Folk Festival program notes - rough drafts, undated (Box-folder 4/12)
    The galley-style sheets have been relocated to box-folder 12/26. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: National Folk Festival programs (rough drafts). This folder is in the current folder.
  - National Folk Festival program notes, undated (Box-folder 12/26)
    Typed text on long, galley-style sheets. Rough drafts of what appear to be program book notes, with extensive details. The paper is delicate, due to acidity and age. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: National Folk Festival programs (rough drafts). Relocated from box-folder 4/12.
- Series 3: National Folk Festival
  Includes programs, calendars, promotional materials, and publicity. See box-folder 12/5 for National Folk Festival-related materials from 1938.
  Titles for the posters and flyers were created by the archivist.
  - National Folk Festival, 1934 (Box-folder 4/13)
    Photocopied newspaper articles, two copies of a typed flyer with a reminiscences (possibly by Knott), and two photocopies of a typed editorial from St. Louis Post-Dispatch at the close of the 1st National Folk Festival. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: National Folk Festival.
  - National Folk Festival (1/2), 1935 (Box-folder 4/14)
    The photocopied newspaper article has been relocated to box-folder 12/2. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: National Folk Festival; this folder is with the current folder.
  - National Folk Festival (2/2), June 8, 1935 (Box-folder 12/2)
    A photocopied article titled "Mountain Music Plus," reprinted from Stand By (June 8, 1935). A typed note from J.T.W. appears as part of the photocopy in the lower right corner, and is part of the photocopy. Relocated from box-folder 4/14.
  - National Folk Festival (1/2), 1936 (Box-folder 4/15)
    Two original programs and a promotional brochure for the Texas Centennial exposition entitled "What Is the National Folk Festival?" A two-page plan for the exposition has been relocated to box-folder 12/4. The 1936 folder and materials from a later accrual were merged. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: 3rd National Folk Festival. The "National Folk Festival 1936" folder is in the current folder.
  - National Folk Festival (2/2), June 14-21, 1936 (Box-folder 12/4)
    A two-page plan for the Texas Centennial Exposition. Relocated from box-folder 4/15.
  - National Folk Festival, 1937 (Box-folder 4/16)
    Photocopy of the program. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: National Folk Festival.
  - National Folk Festival, 1938 (Box-folder 12/5)
    Includes a typed original document about "Questions which pester me," in addition to photocopies of the festival program cover and newspaper publicity.
  - National Folk Festival (1/2), 1939 (Box-folder 4/17)
    A photocopied article with handwritten notes. The souvenir program for "United States Night" has been relocated to box-folder 12/6.
  - National Folk Festival (2/2), 1939 (Box-folder 12/6)
    Original program for "United States Night." Relocated from box-folder 4/17.
  - National Folk Festival, 1940 (Box-folder 4/18)
    Photocopied newspaper articles.
  - National Folk Festival, April 9, 1941 (Box-folder 12/7)
    The "Special school edition," photocopied from the The Washington Post, dedicated to folk music history and festival coverage. Relocated from box-folder 4/19.
  - National Folk Festival (1/2), 1946 (Box-folder 4/19)
    The original announcement (in fragile condition) has been relocated to box-folder 12/8. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: 12th National Folk Festival 1946. This folder is in the current folder.
  - National Folk Festival (2/2), 1946 (Box-folder 12/8)
    Original manuscript (in fragile condition). Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: 12th National Folk Festival 1946. Relocated from box-folder 4/19.
  - National Folk Festival, 1947 (Box-folder 4/20)
    Correspondence and a photocopied festival program.
  - National Folk Festival, 1948 (Box-folder 4/21)
    Photocopied festival flyer.
  - National Folk Festival, 1949 (Box-folder 12/9)
    Original copy of the program. Relocated from box-folder 1/9.
  - National Folk Festival, 1950 (Box-folder 5/1)
    A photocopied festival flyer.
  - National Folk Festival, 1952 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - National Folk Festival, 1953 (Box-folder 5/3)
    Copies of the original program and a two-page fact sheet on the celebration at the festival of the Louisiana Purchase sesquicentennial.
  - National Folk Festival, 1954 (Box-folder 5/4)
    Copies of the original program.
  - National Folk Festival, 1955 (Box-folder 5/5)
    Copies of the original program and informational correspondence.
  - National Folk Festival, 1957 (Box-folder 5/6)
    An original program and Knott's essay on her work behind the scenes of this festival. These items were received as part of the 1979 accrual.
  - National Folk Festival, 1959 (Box-folder 5/7)
    A photocopied festival flyer, blank festival letterhead, and a photocopied newspaper article.
  - National Folk Festival, 1960 (Box-folder 5/8)
    A photocopied festival flyer, an informational flyers, and a photocopied newspaper article.
  - National Folk Festival, 1964 (Box-folder 5/9)
    An original program. The folder was received at AFC with the same title, and is in the current folder.
  - National Folk Festival, 1966 (Box-folder 5/10)
    Informational correspondence, an original program, and a newspaper clipping.
  - National Folk Festival, 1967 (Box-folder 5/11)
    The original folder had two copies of a one-page typed letter to "Friends of the Syracuse Folk Festival," probably written by Knott, with an overview of plans for the festival, and an original copy of the program for the 30th National Folk Festival, in Syracuse. A later accrual of materials for this year was merged with this folder, and includes festival programs, a centennial issue of Grange: National Magazine of Rural America (November 1967), correspondence, newspaper and magazine clippings, informational correspondence, and announcements. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: 30th National Folk Festival program/Syracuse, New York. This folder is in the current folder.
  - National Folk Festival (1/2), 1968 (Box-folder 5/12)
    The contents of three folders have been merged. The current folder includes informational flyers, a photocopied newspaper article, and informational communications and announcements. One of the original folders is in the current folder, with the heading: National Folk Festival program/Milwaukee, Wisconsin, 1968. Two original programs have been moved to box-folder 12/14.
  - National Folk Festival (2/2), 1968 (Box-folder 12/14)
    Two original copies of the program. Relocated from box-folder 5/12.
  - National Folk Festival, 1969 (Box-folder 5/13)
    Contents include an original program from the 32nd National Folk Festival, and an original page of information for participants, with handwritten notes. A copy of the festival program plus informational correspondence were added to this folder from a later accrual. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: 32 [32nd] National Folk Festival [National Folk Festival] Knoxville, Tenn. This folder is in the current folder.
  - National Folk Festival, 1971 (Box-folder 5/14)
    Promotional materials and original programs. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: National Folk Festival program.
  - National Folk Festival, 1972 (Box-folder 5/15)
    Promotional materials and original programs, photos taken at the festival (relocated to Series 10; see PH27-PH51 ), broadsides, two copies of the program, the workshop schedule, the event schedule in calendar form, and a promotional mailing with layouts of photocopied clippings. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: National Folk Festival program.
  - National Folk Festival poster, 1972, AFC 1979/112: GR01; 3 posters, color, 23 3/4 in. x 12 in. (Box-folder 12/28)
    Three copies of the same poster design. Handwritten notes on the verso of one poster. Relocated from box-folder 5/15.
  - National Folk Festival, 1973 (Box-folder 5/16)
    Copies of the program, plus promotional materials, broadsides, and a promotional mailing with layouts of photocopied clippings. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: National Folk Festival program, etc. [sic]
  - National Folk Festival poster, 1973, AFC 1979/112: GR02; 2 posters, color, 22 3/4 in. x 12 in. (Box-folder 12/29)
    Two copies of the same poster design. Relocated from box-folder 5/16.
  - National Folk Festival, 1974 (Box-folder 5/17)
    Copies of the program, an original newspaper clipping, promotional materials, press releases, and broadsides. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: National Folk Festival program, etc.
  - National Folk Festival poster, 1974, AFC 1979/112: OS01-GR03; 2 posters, color, 25 1/8 in. x 17 in. (Oversize folder OS01)
    Two copies of the same poster design. Relocated from box-folder 5/17.
  - National Folk Festival, 1975 (Box-folder 6/1)
    Copies of the program, plus press releases, promotional materials, and a poster. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: National Folk Festival program, etc.
  - National Folk Festival poster, 1975, AFC 1979/112: OS01-GR04; 1 poster, color, 25 in. x 9 1/4 in. (Oversize folder OS01)
    Relocated from box-folder 6/1.
  - National Folk Festival poster, 1975, AFC 1979/112: OS01-GR05; 2 posters, color, 26 in. x 12 in. (Oversize folder OS01)
    Two copies of the same poster design. Printed as a flyer that could be folded and mailed. Relocated from box-folder 6/1.
  - National Folk Festival, 1976 (Box-folder 6/2)
    Copies of the program, plus promotional materials, and a poster. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: National Folk Festival program, etc.
  - National Folk Festival poster, 1976, AFC 1979/112: OS01-GR06; 1 poster, color, 25 in. x 9 1/4 in. (Oversize folder OS01)
    Relocated from box-folder 6/2.
  - National Folk Festival (1/2), 1977 (Box-folder 6/3)
    The original program was received by itself in a folder, and this was merged with a folder of materials from a later accrual, which included another copy of the program, four broadsides, and a promotional flyer for "Folklore in America" (a three-week summer seminar). Three promotional flyers have been relocated to box-folder 12/17. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: National Folk Festival Program/Wolf Trap. This folder is in the current folder.
  - National Folk Festival (2/2), 1977 (Box-folder 12/17)
    Three promotional flyers: one flyer for "Folklore in America" (a three-week summer seminar) and two flyers announcing the 1977 National Folk Festival. Relocated from box-folder 6/3.
  - National Folk Festival, 1978 (Box-folder 6/4)
    Materials from three folders have been merged into one folder: 1) one original program, 2) materials from a later accrual with copies of the program, plus fold-out calendars, and 3) a section from the newspaper Unicorn Times. Another copy of the festival program was added from unsorted materials received in a later accrual. The newspaper section has been relocated to box-folder 12/21. One of the folders received at AFC has the heading: 40th National Folk Festival. This folder is in the current folder.
  - National Folk Festival, July 1978 (Box-folder 12/21)
    A section from the newspaper Unicorn Times, with articles on participants in the upcoming festival. Relocated from box-folder 6/4.
  - National Folk Festival, 1979 (Box-folder 6/5)
    Copies of the program, plus copies of the fold-out calendar, and a poster. A newspaper clipping has been relocated to box-folder 12/22. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: National Folk Festival program, etc. [sic]
  - "High Notes, Tall Tales," July 30, 1979 (Box-folder 12/22)
    A newspaper clipping from the Washington Post about the festival. This is the second part of an article; the first part was not found with this clipping. Relocated from box-folder 6/5.
  - National Folk Festival poster, 1979, AFC 1979/112: GR07; 1 poster, color, 22 5/16 in. x 17 7/16 in. (Box-folder 12/30)
    Relocated from box-folder 6/5.
  - National Folk Festival, 1980 (Box-folder 6/6)
    Copies of the program, plus copies of the fold-out calendar. The newspaper clippings have been relocated to box-folder 12/24. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: National Folk Festival program, etc.
  - Newspaper clippings about the National Folk Festival, July 11-12, 1980 (Box-folder 12/24)
    Newspaper clippings: one page from the Washington Post, with a small section of publicity for the festival (July 11, 1980), and a two-page report on the festival from the Washington Star (July 12, 1980). Relocated from box-folder 6/6.
  - National Folk Festival poster, 1980, AFC 1979/112: GR08; 2 posters, color, 22 2/16 in. x 17 1/16 in. (Box-folder 12/31)
    Two copies of the same poster design. Printed as a flyer that could be folded and mailed. Relocated from box-folder 6/6.
  - National Folk Festival, 1981 (Box-folder 6/7)
    Copies of the program, and copies of the fold-out calendar. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: National Folk Festival program, etc.
  - National Folk Festival poster, 1981, AFC 1979/112: GR09; 2 posters, color, 19 in. x 13 7/8 in. (Box-folder 12/32)
    Two copies of the same poster design. Printed as a flyer that could be folded and mailed. Relocated from box-folder 6/7.
  - National Folk Festival programs, 1940-1948 (Box-folder 12/33)
    One copy each of original programs from various National Folk Festivals. The photocopied first page for 1947 and 1948 are in box-folders 4/20 and 4/21, respectively.
  - National Folk Festival programs, 1950-1968 (Box-folder 12/34)
    One copy each of original programs from various National Folk Festivals. See related materials in box-folders 5/1 (1950), 5/2 (1952), 5/7 (1959), 5/8 (1960), and 12/14 (1968).
  - National Folk Festival, 1982 (Box-folder 6/8)
    Copies of the program, an original letter from Lee Udall to Alan Jabbour, a photocopy of the workshop schedule (accompanied by the letter), and copies of the fold-out calendar. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: National Folk Festival program, etc.
  - National Folk Festival, 1983 (Box-folder 6/9)
    A copy of the program, plus photocopied news clippings. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: National Folk Festival program, etc.
  - National Folk Festival, 1984 (Box-folder 6/10)
    A copy of the program. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: National Folk Festival program, etc.
  - National Folk Festival, 1985 (Box-folder 6/11)
    A photocopy of the program, and two original fold-out calendars. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: National Folk Festival program, etc.
  - National Folk Festival, 1986 (Box-folder 6/12)
    An original copy of the program. Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: National Folk Festival program, etc.
  - 65th National Folk Festival - supplement to various newspapers, August 9-10, 2003 (Box-folder 12/23)
    Original copy of the newspaper supplement/festival program.
- Series 4: The Folk Festival Movement in the United States
  A draft or proposal for a book suggested to Dr. Leonard Roberts for his consideration, with this as the working title, and contributions by various authors including Knott. The intention was to document the folk festival movement and in particular Knott's role in the creation and development of the National Folk Festival Association. Includes handwritten notes from Knott. At the time of this proposal's compilation, Roberts was the director of the Appalachian Studies Center, Pikesville College, Pikesville, Kentucky.
  - The Folk Festival Movement in the United States, Book 1A, 1934-1976 (Box-folder 7/1)
    Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Book IA The Folk Festival Movement in the United States, 1934-1976. See the scope and content note for Series 4 for further details.
  - The Folk Festival Movement in the United States, Book 1B, 1934-1976 (Box-folder 7/2)
    Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Book IB [The Folk Festival Movement in the United States, 1934-1976]. See the scope and content note for Series 4 for further details.
  - The Folk Festival Movement in the United States, Book 2A, 1934-1976 (Box-folder 7/3)
    Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Book IIA The Folk Festival Movement in the United States, 1934-1976. See the scope and content note for Series 4 for further details.
  - The Folk Festival Movement in the United States, Book 2B, 1934-1976 (Box-folder 7/4)
    Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Book IIB [The Folk Festival Movement in the United States, 1934-1976]. See the scope and content note for Series 4 for further details.
  - The Folk Festival Movement in the United States, Book 3A, 1934-1976 (Box-folder 7/5)
    Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Book IIIA The Folk Festival Movement in the United States, 1934-1976. See the scope and content note for Series 4 for further details.
  - The Folk Festival Movement in the United States, Book 3B, 1934-1976 (Box-folder 7/6)
    Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Book IIIB [The Folk Festival Movement in the United States, 1934-1976]. See the scope and content note for Series 4 for further details.
  - The Folk Festival Movement in the United States, Book 4A, 1934-1976 (Box-folder 8/1)
    Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Book IVA The Folk Festival Movement in the United States, 1934-1976. See the scope and content note for Series 4 for further details.
  - The Folk Festival Movement in the United States, Book 4B, 1934-1976 (Box-folder 8/2)
    Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Book IVB [The Folk Festival Movement in the United States, 1934-1976]. See the scope and content note for Series 4 for further details.
  - The Folk Festival Movement in the United States, Book 5A, 1934-1976 (Box-folder 8/3)
    Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Book VA The Folk Festival Movement in the United States, 1934-1976. See the scope and content note for Series 4 for further details.
  - The Folk Festival Movement in the United States, Book 5B, 1934-1976 (Box-folder 8/4)
    Received at AFC in a folder with the heading: Book VB [The Folk Festival Movement in the United States, 1934-1976]. See the scope and content note for Series 4 for further details.
  - The Folk Festival Movement in the United States, Book 5C, 1934-1976 (Box-folder 8/5)